<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Miguel's research page on Miguel Neves</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Miguel's research page on Miguel Neves</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://miguelj-neves.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Complex M5.1 Earthquake Rupture in Sparta, North Carolina</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/sparta/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/sparta/</guid><description>On August 9, 2020, a Mw5.1 earthquake ruptured the uppermost Crust near the town of Sparta, North Carolina. The earthquake ruptured a 2-km-long surface and is likely the first surface-rupturing event in the Eastern United States since the New Madrid earthquake sequence (Figueiredo et al., 2022). Following the mainshock, 5 temporary seismic stations were also deployed by scientists from CERI@Univ. Memphis (Horton et al., 2021) in the area. Together with state-of-the-art earthquake detection and relocation techniques, this sequence provides an opportunity to better understand the local fault structures and the source processes of intraplate earthquakes.</description></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/contact/</guid><description> Email: neves@geoazur.unice.fr GitHub LinkedIn</description></item><item><title>Dynamic Earthquake Triggering in East Africa</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/dynamic_triggering/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/dynamic_triggering/</guid><description>We present evidence of earthquake dynamic triggering in southeast Africa. We analysed seismic waveforms recorded at 53 broad-band and short-period stations in order to identify possible increases in the rate of microearthquakes and tremor due to the passage of teleseismic waves generated by the Mw8.6 2012 Indian Ocean earthquake. We found evidence of triggered local earthquakes and no evidence of triggered tremor in the region. We assessed the statistical significance of the increase in the number of local earthquakes using β-statistics.</description></item><item><title>Improving Iberia's Earthquake Catalog using Machine Learning</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/iberia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/iberia/</guid><description>Under construction</description></item><item><title>Miguel's research page</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/about/</guid><description>About Me I am a PhD candidate of Geophysics at the Georgia Institute of Technology where I study Seismology.
My research focuses on systematic analysis of large seismic datasets with the goal of learning new insights into the physics of earthquakes and active seismic structures. I use the improved catalogs to study earthquake physics, with particular attention to earthquake interactions, source processes and earthquake nucleation in both interplate and intraplate regions.</description></item><item><title>Research Projects</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/</guid><description> The 2004 M6 Parkfield, California, Earthquake Sequence
Improving Iberia&amp;rsquo;s Earthquake Catalog using Machine Learning
Complex M5.1 Earthquake Rupture in Sparta, North Carolina
Dynamic Earthquake Triggering in East Africa</description></item><item><title>The 2004 M6 Parkfield, California, Earthquake Sequence</title><link>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/parkfield/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://miguelj-neves.github.io/research/parkfield/</guid><description>We compiled an high-resolution matched filter relocated earthquake catalog for the 2004 Mw 6 Parkfield earthquake sequence in central California. The relocated catalog spans from 6 November 2003 to 28 March 2005 and contains 13,914 earthquakes, which is about three times the number of events listed in the Northern California Seismic Network catalog. Our results on the seismicity rate changes before the 2004 mainshock do not show clear precursory signals, although we find an increase in the seismic activity in the creeping section of the San Andreas fault (SAF) (about ∼ 30 km northwest of the mainshock epicenter) in the weeks prior to the mainshock.</description></item></channel></rss>